Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue
our series on Ozempic
as we look at the potential side
effects of GLP-1 weight-loss drugs,
such as suicide, pancreatitis,
bowel obstruction,
thyroid cancer,
and pancreatic cancer.
GLP-1 weight-loss drugs.
How safe are they?
Regulatory authorities
have expressed concerns
about the potential risk
of acute pancreatitis,
thyroid cancer,
and kidney failure,
warnings that are
appropriately conveyed
in every box of drugs
handed to a patient.
Here’s the actual package insert
for high-dose Ozempic,
sold for weight loss as Wegovy.
Warnings and precautions
include thyroid tumors,
acute inflammation
of the pancreas,
acute gallbladder disease,
heightened risk
of low blood sugars
if you’re on blood
sugar-lowering medications,
acute kidney injury,
allergic reactions,
worsening eye disease
for those with type 2 diabetes,
an increase in heart rate
that should be monitored,
and suicidal thoughts
and behaviors.
And the package insert
for the other major
GLP-1 weight loss drug,
tirzepatide, sold as Zepbound,
reads almost word for word
the same.
Let’s start with the good news,
suicide.
The possibility of an adverse
psychiatric event on GLP-1 drugs
is biologically plausible
because GLP-1 receptors
are widely expressed
in the central nervous system,
including our brain.
So, what does the science show?
This meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
did not highlight
any detrimental effect
on these drugs on mental health,
including suicide.
Now, this meta-analysis
only covered studies
up through the end of 2023
and only clinical trials,
and those with mental illnesses
are usually excluded
from such studies.
But there have been
newer studies done
with subjects
out in the real world,
and again,
no clear increased risk.
And this study,
on the association
of the Ozempic drug semaglutide
with risk of suicidal ideation
in another cohort
found that the drug
was associated
with a lower risk
for incident and recurrent
suicidal ideation,
apparently cutting
suicidal thoughts
by more than half,
compared to those
on the older, less effective
weight-loss drugs.
After all,
a weight-reducing treatment
that limits
the burden of obesity
could improve mood.
I told you suicide
was the good news!
Now, on to cancer.
Both Wegovy, high-dose Ozempic,
and Zepbound (tirzepatide),
carry so-called
black box warnings
for thyroid cancer risk.
Black box warnings
are the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration’s
strictest caution
about potentially
life-threatening hazards.
In rodents, these drugs
cause dose-dependent
and duration-dependent
thyroid tumors
at clinically relevant
exposures,
meaning the kind of doses
prescribed to humans.
Now, we don’t know yet
whether these drugs cause
a thyroid cancer called
medullary thyroid carcinoma,
which is a cancer of
the thyroid C cells in humans.
To be on the safe side,
the drugs shouldn’t
be prescribed
for high-risk individuals,
like those with a personal
or family history
of thyroid cancer,
but it’s not like the rats
had thyroid cancer
running in their families.
Doctors should counsel
their patients
to remain alert
for symptoms of thyroid tumors,
like a lump
or swelling in the neck,
trouble swallowing,
shortness of breath,
or persistent hoarseness.
I’d be curious in the comments
to see if any viewers
who’ve been prescribed
these drugs
were told any of this
by their prescribing physicians.
Can’t we just ultrasound
people’s necks
to see if they develop
thyroid tumors on these drugs?
That’s considered to be
of uncertain value,
since no such studies
have been done.
Now, there have been
studies done
on GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
and the risk of thyroid cancer
in people.
Researchers found increased risk
of all thyroid cancers
and specifically,
medullary thyroid cancer
in people using these drugs,
particularly after taking them
for a few years.
A commentary
citing the study asked,
"Is it the time
to be concerned?"
Maybe that one study
was just a fluke?
No, after putting together
all the best studies,
a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
found, again,
a significant increase
in the risk
of overall thyroid cancer,
about 52 percent greater odds.
That sounds bad,
until you realize
just how rare
the cancer is overall.
The incidence of thyroid cancer
in this kind of population
is 0.285 cases
per 1,000 patient years.
This means that
over a span of 10 years,
we’d only expect
about three people out of 1,000
to get that cancer.
So, even if you bump up
that risk by 50 percent,
you’re still only talking
about four in 1,000
getting it over a decade,
compared to three in 1,000
if you hadn’t started
taking the drugs.
That translates to a five-year
"number needed to harm"
of 1,349.
That means that even if this
were truly cause-and-effect,
it would take treating
1,349 people for five years
to cause a single additional
case of thyroid cancer.
And even if you’re
the unlucky soul who gets it,
it’s pretty mild, as cancers go.
The five-year
relative survival rate,
meaning the likelihood
you’ll still be alive
five years after diagnosis
compared to people
without the cancer
is 98.4 percent.
Okay, but what about the risk
of pancreatic cancer
with the use of these drugs?
That has a relative
five-year survival rate
of only 12.8 percent.
For thyroid cancer,
a bunch of people are
diagnosed with it,
but very few die from it,
whereas for pancreatic cancer,
almost everyone who gets it
dies from it.
So, do these drugs cause
pancreatic cancer?
That’s exactly the question
I’ll address next.
The most common
adverse side effects
of Ozempic-type
weight-loss drugs
are gastrointestinal issues,
including nausea, vomiting,
diarrhea, and constipation,
but Ozempic may also heighten
the risk of pancreatitis,
kidney failure,
and thyroid cancer.
Many of the kidney issues
may stem from dehydration
due to excessive vomiting
or diarrhea
caused by the drugs,
but what
about the pancreas inflammation?
Analyzing
the prescription records
of 16 million Americans,
compared to taking
an older class
of weight-loss drugs,
the use of GLP-1 drugs
like Ozempic
was associated with nine times
more pancreatitis,
as well as four times
higher risk
of bowel obstruction.
Remember, GLP-1 slows down
your digestive tract.
That’s part of the reason
people get nauseous and barfy,
but that’s also part of why
you feel fuller for longer
and lose weight.
But sometimes, it can
make your gut so sluggish,
it stops working,
and you get a blockage
that could become
a surgical emergency.
It’s super rare, though.
The number needed to harm
after one year of use is 1,223,
meaning that
more than 1,000 people
would have to take the drug
for a year
to cause a single extra case
of bowel obstruction.
So, even after 10 years
of treatment,
your cumulative risk
would be less than one percent.
But what about this 800 percent
increased risk of pancreatitis?
Digestive hormones like GLP-1
act on multiple targets
within the body,
with multiple effects,
perhaps more "magic shotgun"
than "magic bullet,"
but maybe not so magical
for the pancreas.
GLP-1 receptors are
expressed abundantly
throughout the pancreas,
and in response
to GLP-1 therapy,
the cells of the pancreas
proliferate,
swelling the organ
and potentially
squeezing off ducts,
causing inflammation,
at least in rats,
but that led to human studies
like this,
suggesting that GLP-1 drugs
may increase the odds
of pancreatitis
as much as six-fold.
This led some investigators
to conclude
that the balance of evidence
suggests an association
between the use
of GLP-1 based therapies
and acute pancreatitis.
The major concern
is not pancreatitis, though.
Acute pancreatitis is
unpleasant enough,
but the major concern is
subclinical, asymptomatic
inflammation of the pancreas,
because inflammation
of the pancreas
is well known to predispose
to pancreatic cancer,
which is one of the deadliest
forms of cancer.
And some of the rats did show
potentially premalignant changes
in their pancreases
on these drugs.
The concern is that
the pro-proliferative actions
of GLP-1 could take
premalignant lesions
and accelerate their progression
towards cancer.
Remember how these drugs
were modeled off a compound
found in Gila monster saliva?
Few have paused to wonder why
they would produce it.
The answer is that
the Gila monster
is a desert lizard that goes
for weeks or even months
between meals
and conserves energy
during those intervals
by shrinking
its digestive tract,
including its pancreas.
So, when it finally does eat,
it needs a way
to rapidly proliferate
its tissues.
After reviewing thousands
of pages of documents
obtained through
freedom of information requests,
a British Medical Journal
investigation
unearthed unpublished data
from animal and human studies
that point to pathological
changes in the pancreas,
including attempts
by drug companies
to suppress scientific debate
by withholding
important safety data
from the public.
Why have the companies been
so slow to respond
to this threat?
Because of
the "three monkey paradigm,"
which operates as follows.
Companies are
legally responsible
for monitoring the safety
of their own products,
but obviously can’t be
held responsible
for tackling a safety concern
that does not exist.
A concern that can be
plausibly doubted or denied
carries no legal liability,
whereas one that gives rise
to serious consideration
leaves the door wide open
to lawsuits.
Thus, inviting companies
to monitor the safety
of their own products
provides them
with the strongest
possible incentive
for failing to do so,
an instance of the law
of unintended consequences.
The three monkeys,
who neither hear
nor see nor speak,
have been allowed to flourish
at the heart of our system
for protecting the public.
"After careful reflection,"
wrote a professor of medicine
at the Mayo Clinic,
"most patients and clinicians
may opt to avoid
GLP-1 based drugs
or at least avoid using them
for a prolonged
period of time."
And this was all before
this pivotal study came out,
where researchers obtained
transplant-quality pancreases
from, like, accident victims
who had been taking GLP-1 drugs
for at least a year
before they died,
and every single pancreas
showed abnormalities,
marked enlargement, dysplasia,
and even a few little tumors.
This was all discovered
more than a decade ago, though.
Where are we now?
It remains unclear
whether the use of GLP-1 drugs
is linked to an increased risk
of pancreatic cancer.
But trials
would have to be enormous
to exclude an increased risk,
and unless the rules
change radically
by the time
they are to be reported,
most of the data
will remain hidden
from independent scrutiny.
And as one Johns Hopkins
drug safety researcher asked,
"The fundamental question is
who bears the burden
of the passage of time
while these debates
are settled?"
Thousands
of pancreatic cancer cases
have been reportedly tied
to GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
based on the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration’s
Adverse Events Reporting System,
but adverse event databases
that rely on voluntary reporting
are limited by the potential
for reporting bias.
That’s like the Centers
for Disease Control’s
VAERS database,
the Vaccine Adverse Events
Reporting System.
During COVID,
the more states were inclined
to vote Republican,
the more likely their vaccine
recipients or clinicians
were to report
COVID vaccine side effects;
so, maybe there was some kind
of similar reporting bias
among those who submit
their pancreatic cancer
to the FDA?
Either way, if there is
even a remote chance
that certain drugs
can have an impact
on cancer development
and progression,
then such risks
should not be taken lightly.
But if you really don’t want
to get cancer,
then you really don’t want
to be overweight.
Based on a study
following millions of people,
the longer you’re overweight
or obese,
the higher your apparent risk
of 18 different kinds of cancer.
So, even if you cared
only about cancer,
might these drugs actually lower
your overall cancer risk
if they caused
enough weight loss?
A meta-analysis
of bariatric surgery studies
found that those
going under the knife
tend to lose so much weight
that they have
a significantly lower risk
of getting cancer
and appear to cut
their risk of dying from cancer
nearly in half.
This modeling study suggests
that widespread usage
of these new-generation
weight-loss drugs, like Ozempic,
could prevent more than,
like, 1 out of 100 cancers
over the next 25 years.
And that’s just cancer.
Wouldn’t just
the cardiovascular benefits
of losing a lot of weight alone
outweigh any potential risks?
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.